<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>WifiCIDR Blog (Posts about math)</title><link>https://blog.wificidr.net/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://blog.wificidr.net/categories/math.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:djustice@wificidr.net"&gt;Daniel Justice&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 02:21:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Circles and Parabolas</title><link>https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/parabola/circles-and-parabolas/</link><dc:creator>Daniel Justice</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="A-few-notes-on-circles-and-tangents"&gt;A few notes on circles and tangents&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/parabola/circles-and-parabolas/#A-few-notes-on-circles-and-tangents"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have been &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; slowly making my way through Paul Lockhart's "Measurement".  It is a fantastic book, and I highly recommend it for anyone who enjoys math as a hobby or pastime.  One of the questions posed is to find the radius of the smaller, nested circle given the radius of the two larger circles (all tangent to each other and the line below them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/54/Sangaku_Circles.JPG/514px-Sangaku_Circles.JPG" alt=""&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I struggled with this problem for much longer than I care to admit, and I struggled with whether or not to even write this post.  I'm not terribly clever with writing, or math for that matter, but I hope others who are slogging their way through work or school will find a bit of encouragment by the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="Lessons-learned"&gt;Lessons learned&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/parabola/circles-and-parabolas/#Lessons-learned"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The internet is at most of our fingertips, and it is much too easy to search for the answers to all of our questions.  I think much of my own personal struggle in mathematics has been due to the fact that I am lazy.  It's true.  I'd much rather watch &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC1_uAIS3r8Vu6JjXWvastJg"&gt;Mathologer&lt;/a&gt; perform magic in front of my eyes than actually &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; math.  However, just like exercising, finding my way to the end usually provides the motivation to continue the next time around.  I hope through continued practice and discovery that I will build up the skills and tools to make this a little less painful as I attempt other problems.  Think of watching Danny MacAskill doing amazing tricks on his bicycle.  What we don't see are the endless hours of &lt;strong&gt;practice&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;repeated failure&lt;/strong&gt; that led to amazing moments.  This is true of every profession, but I seem to need to remind myself of it daily!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="Two-circles-tangent-to-a-line"&gt;Two circles tangent to a line&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/parabola/circles-and-parabolas/#Two-circles-tangent-to-a-line"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The way I attacked this problem may be the most naive thing you have ever seen, but I made some personal discoveries along the way that I haven't seen in the textbooks at my disposal.  Let's start with two circles tangent to each other and a horizontal line.  Grab a piece of scrap paper and draw a few examples.  Fix the radius of one circle, and vary the radius of the other.  I have a stencil with various sizes of circles on it.  I found it much easier to use for this problem than simply relying on a compass.  The traditional approach to this problem is to use triangles and a few applications of the Pythagorean theorum.  Don't forget my disclaimer about a naive approach!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you notice a pattern drawn by the centers of the tangential circles?  They follow a quadratic curve (parabola) away from the fixed circle.  After a little poking around in an algebra book, I quickly realized that given a fixed circle, the centers of the tangential circles all lie on a parabola where the fixed circle sits at the focus!  Check out the Desmos link below for a demo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/kgnhqs8b5r"&gt;Two circles tangent to one another&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Move the slider around to see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we think about the &lt;a href="https://www.purplemath.com/modules/parabola.htm"&gt;definition of a parabola&lt;/a&gt;, this pattern makes sense.  The vertex sits midway between the focus and the directrix.  The directrix is a fixed line, and a "shortest line" between a point on the parabola and the directrix always hits the directrix at a 90-degree angle.  The focus is a different case as it is a fixed point, not a line.  This means a "shortest line" from the focus to a point on the parabola is a matter of connecting the dots at whatever angle they make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we identify all the "fixed" parts of this setup?  The distance between the focus and the vertex is the same as the distance between the vertex and the directrix.  If we draw a line through the vertex parallel to the directrix, we've identified all the points this fixed distance from the directrix.  What about the focus?  Let's do the same thing.  All the points at this fixed distance around the focus forms a circle lying in the "cup" of the parabola... and tangent to it.  You should be noticing the same pattern here that we saw earlier.  The reason is pretty neat (at least to my pea brain).  By identifying a set of fixed points, we are left with the difference between the circle around the focus and the line through the vertex - and tangent to both!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.wificidr.net/images/parabola-cir.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's use the previous image as an example.  I have identified all of our "fixed points" (the black circle around the focus and the purple line along the x-axis) that are the focal distance from either the focus or the directrix.  If we consider the point (4, 4), it's "shortest line" to the directrix is straight down and interesecting the directrix at a perpedicular angle.  It is also a distance of 4 from the purple line through the vertex (and a distance of 5 to the directrix).  What about the "shortest line" between the focus (0, 1) and (4, 4)?  Well, the horizontal distance is 4, and the vertical distance is 3.  This makes a 3-4-5 triangle, so it is 5 units away from the focus.  That means it is also only 4 units from the circle around the focus.  This means we can sweep a line of length 4 around the point (4, 4) and get a circle that intersects both the circle around the focus &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; the line through the vertex.  Cool, right?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve this problem I noticed that what is true for one circle is also true for the other.  The nested, inner cicle lies at the intersection of the parabolas formed by the two bigger circles.  The algebra gets a little messy since you have to locate one of the parabolas in terms of the other, but the math does work out.  I'm going to present an interactive example instead of a mess of LaTex since the geometry is really the point of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/77xvzr94v1"&gt;The solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://blog.wificidr.net/images/parabola-cir-demo.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Move the slider to see the solution adjust to changing conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="Why-does-it-matter?"&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/parabola/circles-and-parabolas/#Why-does-it-matter?"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;It really doesn't at the end of the day, but I learned something from it even if it was a really long-winded way around to a much simpler problem.  It got me to poking around with parabolas quite a bit even though that wasn't even the point of the question... or was it?  That is the beauty of mathematics to me.  The breadth of material is vast to say the least, but interconnected in interesting and beautiful ways!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>math</category><guid>https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/parabola/circles-and-parabolas/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 01:04:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Project Euler #6</title><link>https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/project-euler-6/project-euler-6/</link><dc:creator>Daniel Justice</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="Project-Euler-problem-6"&gt;Project Euler problem 6&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/project-euler-6/project-euler-6/#Project-Euler-problem-6"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stumbled across Project Euler (at &lt;a href="https://www.hackerrank.com/contests/projecteuler/challenges/euler006"&gt;HackerRank&lt;/a&gt; or at &lt;a href="https://projecteuler.net/"&gt;Project Euler&lt;/a&gt;) a while back, and it has been a low item on my to-do list for some time.  It can be quite frustrating at first, but I find it rewarding each time I unlock a little piece of the mathematical puzzle.  Of course you can cheat, but that completely defeats the purpose and harms no one but yourself.  I hope I can demonstrate why with this example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On a side note, HackerRank typically penalizes you for brute force methods.  They force you to really think about the problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://projecteuler.net/problem=6"&gt;Problem 6&lt;/a&gt; asks, "Find the difference between the sum of the squares of the first one hundred natural numbers and the square of the sum."  In other words, what is 
$$ \big|\big(\sum_1^n n\big)^2 - \big(\sum_1^n n^2\big)\big| $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was already familiar with &lt;a href="http://mathandmultimedia.com/2010/09/15/sum-first-n-positive-integers/"&gt;Gauss's method&lt;/a&gt; of summing the first series of natural numbers.  What I did not know how to do was to sum their squares.  The brute force method will yield a result, but HackerRank will penalize you with a timeout if you go that route.  I chose to dig deeper...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="A-row-of-boxes"&gt;A row of boxes&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/project-euler-6/project-euler-6/#A-row-of-boxes"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nothing beats a little chair time with pencil and paper.  I suspected a strong link between geometry and the answer to this problem, so I started drawing squares on my graph paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.wificidr.net/images/boxes.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;!-- .element height="50%" width="50%" --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are familiar with &lt;a href="https://www.mathsisfun.com/algebra/triangular-numbers.html"&gt;triangle numbers&lt;/a&gt;, you might notice the pattern of the right edge of each square.  It is the series 1, 3, 6, 10, 15...  It is really fascinating to me how these things relate to one another.  The formula to find the nth triangle number is the same formula to find the sum of a series of natural numbers!&lt;br&gt;
$$ \sum_1^n n=\frac{n(n+1)}{2} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, to find the area of the enclosing rectangle, we simply multiply the sum from above by our 'n'.  Now, we need to account for all those little strips of triangle numbers that are left over on top of the squares.  I have to admit, I spent quite a bit of time on this one and simply got stuck.  I knew I needed to find another sum, but this time the series is the sum of the triangle numbers themselves.  I needed to find a formula for the series 1, 4, 10, 20, 35...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="Tetrahedral-Numbers"&gt;Tetrahedral Numbers&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/project-euler-6/project-euler-6/#Tetrahedral-Numbers"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to not ruin the learning process, I did an internet search for the mystery series.  I immediately came across this article on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetrahedral_number"&gt;tetrahedral numbers&lt;/a&gt;.  This was my extra quantity!  To find the sum of a series of squares, subtract the (n - 1)th tetrahedral number from the area of the rectangle that overlays the boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tetrahedral numbers are easily visualized if you think of a triangular tower of spheres as in this image:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/87/Pyramid_of_35_spheres_animation_original.gif" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;By Blotwell [GFDL (http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html), CC-BY-SA-3.0 (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/) or GPL (http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html)], from Wikimedia Commons&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you start taking apart the tower, the spheres perfectly fill in the gaps in the stack of rectangles above.  If you get really bored, you can validate this like I did with a bunch of blocks and marbles.  These items are readily available if you have kids.  One last bit worth noting is that we only need (n - 1) tetrahedral numbers because we don't need to fill in the last row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the sum of a series of squares can be found by:
$$ \sum_1^n n^2=n * \frac{n(n+1)}{2} - \frac{(n - 1)(n)(n+1)}{6} $$&lt;/p&gt;
$$ =\frac{n^3+n^2}{2} - \frac{(n^2-n)(n+1)}{6} $$&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
$$ =\frac{n^3+n^2}{2} - \frac{n^3+n^2-n^2-n}{6} $$&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
$$ =\frac{3(n^3+n^2)}{6} - \frac{n^3-n}{6} $$&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
$$ =\frac{3n^3+3n^2-n^3+n}{6} $$&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
$$ \sum_1^n n^2=\frac{2n^3+3n^2+n}{6} $$&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="Why-does-this-matter?"&gt;Why does this matter?&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/project-euler-6/project-euler-6/#Why-does-this-matter?"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not to sound overly cliché, but it is easy, often too easy, to find answers to all of our questions at our fingertips.  For example, if you want to cut right to the chase, you could have a look at &lt;a href="http://www.mathblog.dk/project-euler-problem-6/"&gt;this answer&lt;/a&gt;.  Be sure to take a look at the &lt;a href="https://trans4mind.com/personal_development/mathematics/series/sumNaturalSquares.htm"&gt;proof&lt;/a&gt; as well.  Both posts are respectable, but I think they hide the intuition in the formulas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my search for an answer I learned something new, and I also saw the problem in a new light not illustrated at either of the previous links.  Pardon my drawing skills, but imagine the previous image as a stack of cubes, all laid on top of one another pushed to one side.  Here's a top-down view of what I'm describing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.wificidr.net/images/stacked_boxes.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;!-- .element height="50%" width="50%" --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you imagine the sum of squares as rows of stacked boxes, you can clearly see the relationship between the sum and the tetrahedral numbers from earlier (the missing space to be subtracted)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I have encouraged you to dig a little deeper the next time you run across a tricky math problem and to look for a deeper understanding of the fundamental forces that shape it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered"&gt;
&lt;div class="input"&gt;
&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;In [ ]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
    &lt;div class="input_area"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>math</category><category>python</category><guid>https://blog.wificidr.net/posts/project-euler-6/project-euler-6/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 02:35:26 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>